
<generator start-xpath="//lookup-table[@key = 'D']/lookup-entry" escape="%">

	<lookup-table key="D">
		<lookup-entry><p>How does the community react to the NPC's family? Well, truthfully, the family %viewsfamily% The NPC has %foes% who would easily %foesviews% Luckily, though, the character also has %allies% and allies who %alliesviews% As for companions, the NPC has %companions% %companionstraits% %parents% The NPC %viewsparents% The NPC %siblings% %viewssiblings% The character's family %family%</p><br/><p>Important Events %events% </p><p>%traits%.</p></lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>
	
	<lookup-table key="traits">
		<lookup-entry><ul>
		<li>Weakness: %weakness%</li>
		<li>Needs: %needs%</li>
		<li>Desires: %desires%</li>
		<li>Enemies: %enemies%</li>
		</ul></lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="parents">
		<lookup-entry>Both of the NPC's parents are alive and well.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Both of the NPC's parents are alive, but one is in poor health.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Both of the NPC's parents are alive, but in poor health.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Only one of the NPC's parents is alive.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Only one of the NPC's parents is alive, and he or she is infirm.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Both of the NPC's parents died after he reached maturity.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Both of the NPC's parents died and he was raised by relatives.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Both of the NPC's parents died and he was raised by friends.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Both of the NPC's parents died, leaving the NPC to fend for themself.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="verb1">
		<lookup-entry>is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>was</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="verb2">
		<lookup-entry>is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>was</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>
	
	<lookup-table key="viewsparents">
		<lookup-entry>idolizes (or idolized) their parents.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>idolizes (or idolized) one of their parents but dislikes the other.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>%verb1% on good terms with their parents.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>has lost contact with their parents or did so prior to their death.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>%verb1% considered a disgrace by their parents.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>%verb1% embarrassed by their parents.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>dislikes (or disliked) their parents.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>fears (or feared) their parents.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>%verb2% great enmity for their parents.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="siblings">
		<lookup-entry>is an only child</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>has an older sibling</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>has a younger sibling</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is the youngest member of a small family of #3R5# children</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is the middle child in a small family of #3R5# children</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is the oldest child of a small family of #3R5# children</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is the youngest child of a large family of #5R14# children</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is a middle child in a large family of #5R14# children</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is the oldest child of a large family of #5R14# children</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="viewssiblings">
		<lookup-entry>who prefers to avoid their contact.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>who they treat in an openly hostile manner.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>who do not recognize their relation.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>who tends to avoid them, if possible.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>who %verb1% bullied and harassed.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>who feels protective towards them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>and %verb1% their protector and provider.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>and %verb1% loved and admired.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>and %verb1% respected and honored.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>who are all deceased.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="family">
		<lookup-entry>is an old, established one and has never lived anywhere else as far as anyone can remember.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>emigrated to their current home many generations ago.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>emigrated one or two generations ago.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>emigrated here recently. They are the first generation born in this area.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>emigrated here by choice after the birth.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>were left behind, who came to this land.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>are refugees forced to flee their home due to war or disaster.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>are exiles forced to leave their homeland for political reasons.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>are fugitives who fled their homeland to avoid jail.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="viewsfamily">
		<lookup-entry>is considered the keystone of the community.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is admired and beloved.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is respected and trusted.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is merely accepted.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is engaged in a quarrel or feud with one other family.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is shunned by the community.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is the subject of dark tales.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is viewed with suspicion.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is reviled and hated.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is considered inconsequential and replaceable.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is sympathetic to their misfortune.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>is considered valuable and provides an essential but common trade.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="foes">
		<lookup-entry>a single important enemy</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>two important enemies, perhaps working together</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a small group of #3R5# people who consider them an enemy</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a group of about ten people who hate them</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>made an enemy of a large group of #10R25# people</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>angered a very large group of #80R110# people</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>earned the hatred of a town or guild-like organization</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>become hated by the inhabitants of an entire city or large institution (like a church or order of knighthood)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>an entire nation or race that considers them an enemy</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="foesviews">
		<lookup-entry>strike(s) at them by attacking their friends, family, and allies.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>hire(s) an assassin to kill them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>want(s) to capture and torture them before killing them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>hire(s) mercenaries to hurt them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>hire(s) saboteur to hinder them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>use(s) arcane magic against them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>will spy on them constantly, providing information to rivals and other enemies.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>use(s) divine magic against them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>turn(s) the local authorities against them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>employ(s) monsters and other exotic creatures against them.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="allies">
		<lookup-entry>a single important friend</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>two important friends</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a small group (about five people) who count them a true friend</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a group of about ten people who honor them</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>won the respect of a large group (about twenty-five people)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>befriended a very large group (about one hundred people)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>earned the respect of a town or guild-like organization</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>found favor with the people of an entire city or large institution (like a church or order of knighthood)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>the love of an entire nation</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="alliesviews">
		<lookup-entry>watch over his friends and family for them.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>can supply funds in a crisis.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>provide them with equipment.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>offer them military training and support.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>can do scholarly research into ancient lore when needed.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>act as spies or informers.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>have access to magic (pick either arcane or divine magic).</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>provide legal or governmental leverage when needed.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>are in league with a powerful monster, perhaps even a dragon.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="companions">
		<lookup-entry>no important companions but appreciates those who are</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a common pet like a house cat, small dog, or song bird. It is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>an unusual pet, like a monkey or dolphin. It is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a guard/hunting animal like a war dog, panther, or falcon. It is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a common mount, like a horse or camel. It is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>an uncommon mount, like an elephant or a worg. It is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a ward, child, or other young companion. It is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>an apprentice, squire, servant, or similar underling who is</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>a spouse, lover, sibling, or similar adult companion who is</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="companionstraits">
		<lookup-entry>nimble and acrobatic.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>clever and skilled/trained.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>determined and spirited.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>especially strong and fierce.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>unusually intelligent</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>very perceptive.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>kind-hearted and loving.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>loyal and devoted.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>known to have dealings with monsters and other exotic creatures.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="events">
		<lookup-entry><BR/>While poking his nose in where it didn't belong, the character saw something that has made them dislike a certain type of monster or race. The character would probably avoid the monster or react emotionally while interacting with it. He might even leap into immediate combat upon seeing the chosen monster or race.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>As he wandered in an unknown neighborhood, the character witnessed an act of kindness which forever endeared members of a certain race to them. The character can make it his goal to help as many of the chosen race as he can, or he can simply have them go out of his way to be nice to them.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character accidentally stumbled upon an important secret and has been sworn to silence. No one, not even his closest friends, is allowed to know what he saw. This secret might cause the character grief by coming between them and his companions. (A good example is knowing that an ally is not what he or she appears to be.)<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>While young, the character was befriended by a person who turned out to be an extreme snob. As a result, the person spurned the character for some seemingly frivolous reason. After that, the character had to deal with derision from the person's other friends. Optimally, the character should be inordinately sensitive to the jibes of others or, by contrast, have discovered his own sense of worth and become immune to most derisive comments.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character spent time with a traveler or adventurer who helped them learn to overcome his childhood fears and become more mature. Choose a specific fear that the traveler helped the character overcome (not including fear auras generated by creatures). Examples include fear of the sea, the dark, closed spaces, open spaces, and so on.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>Through the purest of motives, the character helped a person in need only to discover later that the one he helped harmed another person dear to them. The character displays a certain wariness in situations similar to the one that occurred above.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A carefully thought out plan made by the character and an ally fell apart through unforeseen, chance happenings or by subterfuge on the part of the ally. The results were nearly disastrous and taught the character that even the best plans can fail utterly. One of the results of this past event can be that the character must spend some extra time thinking of contingency plans -- just in case.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>While learning his current profession or working together with someone, the character made an enemy of another person. They have similar goals and interests, but are lifelong rivals. The Dungeon Master can use this background generator to come up with the rival, or let the rival be one of the PCs.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character faced a situation where he had to choose between what he perceived as two evils. Unfortunately, he chose the evil that led to the destruction of something he loved. The character has learned either to think things through thoroughly or to use gut reactions to make decisions.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>When the character learned that his family had some secret in its past, his extreme curiosity led them to root it out. What he discovered was so terrible that it made a lasting impression on them. This event can affect the character in many different ways, such as recurring nightmares, a lack of curiosity, and a secretive attitude.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>One of the character's parents abandoned them when he was little. The character has always felt a great deal of guilt or pain about the whole matter and is now determined to find his true father or mother.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character's early efforts at some manner of artistic endeavor were met with praise, resulting in an interest in that form of art that lasts to this day. Examples of art forms include pottery, metalcrafting, painting, glassblowing, and so on.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character suffered a serious accident due to his own carelessness. Although he has tried to put this mishap behind them, he has been scarred or disfigured in some way. The scar or disfigurement acts as a constant reminder of that grim happening. (It need not have a negative effect on the character's ability scores.)<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A close friend or relative gave his or her own life to save the character during an accident or disaster. The character has never forgotten this sacrifice. The DM must decide who the noble person was and how he or she was related to the character.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>An angry confrontation over a small matter occurred between the character and a friend just before the friend's death. The character carries an intense grief and sense of guilt, perhaps leading them to be morose to repress his anger.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was offered a chance to help found a business, fund a venture, or otherwise participate in a risky undertaking. He turned down the chance and watched as it became even more successful than hoped. Good examples of an appropriate undertaking include founding an inn, being a leader in a group of mercenaries that eventually becomes the core of the city guard, and so on.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was involved in a successful business or other venture. The illegal actions of an underhanded competitor decimated the undertaking, however, showing the character just how cutthroat the real world can be. Now the character is likely to be wary while making business deals, perhaps as rather savvy in business or simply cautious to the point of distrust.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>At one point in the character's life, he found themself in a situation that made them so angry that he couldn't control his temper. The resulting display of uncontrolled rage caused them to alienate someone he loved or lose something very precious to them. Because of the character's earlier display of temper, the he has tightly controlled emotions or sometimes gives in to bouts of reckless anger.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>An aged friend or relative shared the wisdom of his years with the character. These tales and lessons have stuck with them throughout the years. Because of this exposure to wisdom, the character can be played as someone with a story for every occasion.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A close friend or relative of the character gave his life to halt some looming evil, saving the lives of countless people. This sacrifice has been an inspiration to the character, giving them hope even in the darkest hour. Despite any dark traits that the character might have, he gives his all when the stakes are high.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character saved the life of a world-weary traveler and received a gift in exchange for his efforts: a magical +1 weapon. This weapon has a special place in the character's heart, and he will not forsake it for another without excellent cause.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>After almost losing family or friends to brigands or some other criminal element, the character learned the value of laws and those who enforce them. Because of this good exposure to peacekeeping efforts, the character finds it hard to break the local laws or perhaps merely has respect for the local authorities.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A person that the character always had fun with suddenly showed a more commanding aspect when the character least expected it but most needed it. The character watches others carefully now and never underestimate them because of this past experience.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was traveling when his party was attacked by a monster. This attack knocked out several of those who would ordinarily take charge and defend, changing the character's fear to determination to protect the downed ones. With the help of another, he brought down the monster. This exposure to possible death left the character very aware of most people's tenuous link to life. Now he may seem prepared for every eventuality or merely determined to allow everyone to have a chance to live.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was stricken with a grave illness that nearly cost them his life. After an extended period of convalescence, he recovered. This brush with death has left the character with a very real sense of his own mortality and the value of life, resulting in an element of deep caring for others who are ill.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A friend or relative of the character introduced them to the joys of learning and reading. Since that time, he has been fascinated by all manner of tales. The character might keep a library of his own, never traveling without a useful book or two, or perhaps he simply writes down every story he hears.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was raised in an environment that taught them he was the best at a particular challenge or set of challenges (such as sprinting, painting, or other tasks). However, once he left that environment, he found out to his dismay that many other people are better than he is at that pursuit. This experience has either humbled them or led them to become a sarcastic nay-sayer.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A valiant stranger saved the character from a nearly fatal accident. However, the circumstances of the accident have left a strong impression on the character, causing them to fear the recurrence of these circumstances. The character approaches certain situations with overwhelming caution, at times causing another problem to crop up.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character saved a traveling knight from certain death. Since then, the knight has appeared several times to help the character make difficult decisions. While not a mentor, the figure has certainly spurred the character on in his search for adventure and honor. The DM should figure out exactly how the traveler has helped the character recently.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was exposed to many different races and creatures while growing up. As a result, he treats everyone with an equality that sometimes makes others uneasy. The player should decide, with the DM's approval, who and what the character was friends with while growing up.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character has participated in events that could be considered both evil and good. As a result, others around them never know what to expect. The DM could roleplay them as having a neutral viewpoint and, at times, interesting insights into problems. He tends to do things that can be seen as evil, but turn out to be for the greater good. Sometimes his actions cause conflict with others until he can explain themself.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>Earlier in his adventuring career, the character was something of a villain. In time, however, he realized he was a hero at heart. His evil allies now consider them a traitor and may show up to menace them while he's assisting the party. One of the most important things the character has learned is to take personal responsibility for everything he does.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>After showing honor when dealing with a downed foe, the character received a parting gift from them. Either the character's armor or shield (chosen by the player) is a +1 magic item.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>During a moment of bravado, the character challenged an obviously superior foe to a contest of some sort. He was defeated easily and humiliated before his friends. Whether he has learned his lesson or remains bitter is up to the DM. In any event, he now has the ability to see when the odds are against them.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character had a friend or family member who seemed to love and respect them. After a long trip away from the character, the friend or family member came back. The character learned the hard way that this person had picked up an ambitious, self-centered attitude. The DM can decide whether this person is still involved in the character's life or not. If so, the person should occasionally show up and attempt to ruin the character's plans.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>During a fierce battle, the character was wounded and captured by enemies. However, the character waited patiently, studying the enemy's weaknesses and taking advantage of them to escape. The character may now have an appreciation for knowing when to fight and when not to. At times, he counsels others to step away from a tough battle and use guile to win through it.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was resent when a powerful magical spell was cast. In addition to its desired effect, this magic has changed them in some way. The DM should decide exactly what the change might be, but it must be pronounced. For example, perhaps the character is now utterly fascinated by magic and its effects, even if he cannot cast it.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>Someone in the character's life pushed them to become a sorcerer. This either led them into magic or made them realize his limitations in that area. If gifted, the character could be grateful to the person. If not gifted, then the character could have low self-esteem because he can't use sorcery, or he could simply dislike the person who couldn't accept them for who he was.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character has a period in his life of several months which he simply cannot account for. He has no idea where he was during that time or what he did. His desire to learn these things is tempered by his fear of what he may discover. So that a backstory is available when needed, the DM should figure out what happened during this 'lost time.'<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was betrayed by a trusted ally at a critical moment, leaving them with a major wound. Aside from giving them a disfiguring scar or other persistent injury, he now has a deep suspicion of those who have not proven themselves trustworthy. The character may be openly suspicious of others, or quiet around them.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was presented with a very difficult puzzle or challenge which required a great deal of thought to solve. Since that time he has been fascinated with all manner of puzzles, enigmas, and riddles. He shows glee when presented with a new puzzle.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was presented with a very difficult puzzle or challenge which required a great deal of thought to solve. Since that time he has been fascinated with all manner of puzzles, enigmas, and riddles. He shows glee when presented with a new puzzle.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>While exploring an ancient ruin, the character found a magical relic. Upon researching it, he discovered it once belonged to one of his ancestors. The properties of the item are up to the DM. As a rule, it should have the ability to mimic a 1st-level spell once per day.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character crossed an evil magician and has been afflicted with a curse. The exact nature of the curse must be determined by the DM. Possible game effects include the reduction of an ability score or a penalty to a difficulty modifier for some actions.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A beloved friend, relative, or ally of the character vanished under mysterious circumstances some time ago. The character fears the missing person may be dead but hopes this is not the case. The character may dedicate themself to finding this person or, at the very least, discovering his or her fate.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>In order to prove his skills, master the power of magic, or otherwise claim his place as an adventurer, the character underwent a tremendous ordeal. Whether he triumphed at a great cost is up to the player. If he failed, the character constantly struggles to undo this shame.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was forced from his home and now must wander the lands until certain conditions have been met. Once he meets these conditions, he can return to the place and people that are uppermost in his heart. The DM should figure out where the character was forced from and what he has to do to return. If he wishes, the conditions can be of medium or extreme difficulty.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character has learned that once beloved members of his family oppose them in various ways (some are even evil). He knows that though he wants to do good, some family members see his actions as evil. Whether the character wishes to oppose his relatives, for whom he still has strong feelings, is up to the player.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was entrusted with the care of a youngster, possibly a sibling or relative. As the child grew, it became clear that he or she was not the character his or her protector was. This youth has become corrupt, perhaps even a true villain. Although the character probably blames themself for this tragedy, he still loves his ward very much. It is up to the DM whether the character still wishes to help the person onto the path of good.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character learned all kinds of useful facts while growing up. As a result, he can relate some obscure fact about almost every subject. Feel free to roleplay the character as a person eager to impart the information that he knows, or play them as someone who imparts his knowledge only when it is needed.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character played a critical role in helping prevent some tragic or deadly circumstances from becoming worse than they could have been. Although he didn't succeed in averting all deaths or calamities, his work has left those involved grateful to them. The DM should decide who the character helped and what tragedy occurred.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>Prior to becoming an adventurer, the character had a comfortable home and a very stable life. Some natural disaster ruined this happiness, however, leaving the character alone. Because his home was destroyed, play them as someone who feels he can't settle down anywhere. He might act jealous of others who seem to have the happiness he seeks.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character discovered extensive corruption in the government of his homeland. He now lives with strong shame of his heritage. Whether he actively opposes the homeland is up to the DM.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character is not what he appears to be, although it may be that only he believes this. The character is actually an intelligent monster, humanoid, or other creature who has been transformed into this shape. Exactly how this happened should be decided by the DM. Perhaps a spell affected them, morphing his shape into its current one.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>After living at a certain higher standard than his current status allows, the character often wishes for things he can't afford. The character may yearn fruitlessly for these luxuries -- or try to acquire them.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>Because of illness or injury, the character had to deal with a health condition that took away his hearing or sight temporarily. As a result, he has a sense of compassion for others in the same situation. Before play, the DM should figure out which sense was affected and when the character lost it.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>After a savage attack that left them close to death, the character is healed by a cleric (possibly the party's cleric). The character periodically seeks guidance from this cleric. The DM and the cleric's player should decide the circumstances of the NPC's first appearance so the DM can make them appear again in an appropriate manner.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A mentor of the character leaves for a long journey. When he or she comes back, the mentor has changed profoundly. Not only is the mentor a cleric now, but he or she also seems to have found a deep inner peace. The character may be so impressed that he wishes to follow the mentor's path.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A mentor of the character leaves for a long journey. When he or she comes back, the mentor has changed profoundly. Not only is the mentor a cleric now, but he or she also seems to have found a deep inner peace. The character may be so impressed that he wishes to follow the mentor's path.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character witnessed a terrible magical accident. This taught them respect for arcane and divine powers. Depending on how bad the accident was, the character may respect magic or, taken to the extreme, fear it.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>One of the character's acquaintances (past or present) has a closely-guarded item in his or her possession. The acquaintance occasionally does (or did) things that piqued the character's curiosity. If the acquaintance is still present, the DM needs to decide what the item is and when the acquaintance will show up again to tantalize the character further.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>After being murdered, a close friend of the character returned from the grave as a ghost or other undead creature. He tormented the character's homeland until the character's own hand sent the creature to oblivion. The trauma of this event has given the character a phobia of the undead. He could take this phobia to an extreme, incinerating corpses where he finds them, avoiding graveyards, and so on.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>One of the most influential people in the character's life taught them the meaning and use of discipline. However, as the character learned more from this person, he realized that the mentor had no compassion for others who couldn't hold up under the discipline. Although the character most likely has a good sense of discipline, he understands that everyone is different and can't necessarily follow the beat of the same drummer that he follows.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A close friend of the character was arrested for a crime he or she did not commit. Despite evidence of his or her innocence presented by the character, the friend was convicted and executed. This bitter lesson about power and its abuse has stuck with the character. As a result, he has no liking for rules or leaders.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was once arrested for a crime he did not commit. Although his guilt seemed certain, the perceptive magistrate in the case sought out the truth before allowing a sentence to come down on the character's head. The character's faith in courts and legal systems was shaped by this encounter.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character has stepped down from a position of authority over others. Perhaps he has renounced his claim to the throne or simply given up on the idea of managing the family business. He may be very reluctant to accept the role of leader, even among his closest friends.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character is related to or associated with one of the PCs in the campaign. The DM determines which PC the character has an association with. The roll of a d20 determines how closely the two are related or associated. A low score (1-6) indicates very close ties, while a high value (14-20) marks a distant relationship. A mid-range roll (7-13) indicates a moderately close relationship.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character's religious faith was tested when he discovered high levels of corruption in a church organization. After speaking out against the wrongdoers, he found themself ostracized and forced to leave the area. The character now doubts the integrity of any organized religion or its followers.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>A large number of the character's friends and relatives died in a dragon attack. The full extent of this disaster is up to the DM, but it has left the character with a great hatred for dragons.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character had extensive contact with the military, for good or evil, and puts great faith in the need for order and discipline. The character's belief extends into his home life and his relationships, making them something of a controlling figure.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character has experienced the oppression of a tyrannical military or theocratic state first hand. Perhaps he was a prisoner of war or an officer who saw inherent flaws in the plans of his superiors. As a result, he has lost all respect for authority figures and believes that only the corrupt rise to positions of power.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character discovered that some authority figure he respected was actually corrupt. This may have been a personal betrayal or simply a failure to uphold the standards of his or her office. Before the character could confront the villain, however, he or she vanished with a valuable treasure. Now the character stalks this criminal, determined to right the wrong that he or she has done.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was once on the losing end of a battle. While he escaped with his life, countless others were not so fortunate. The victor in that battle is determined to complete his mission, however, which means that all survivors (including the character) must be hunted down and destroyed. The DM should identify this enemy from the existing campaign. <BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>During a long journey, the character's expedition met with disaster, leaving them badly wounded. Although he did eventually recover, two of his senses have been badly impaired by the accident. The nature of the character's handicaps can be used to determine the type of disaster.<blockquote>Two rolls of a d20 determine the affected senses:<BR/>1-4 indicates sight<BR/>5-8 indicates hearing<BR/>9-12 indicates smell<BR/>13-16 indicates touch<BR/>17-20 indicates taste</blockquote></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was exposed to a virulent plague that decimated his village. This left his physical health shattered. The DM must select either Strength, Dexterity, or Constitution, and reduce its score to 5 to reflect this weakness.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character was exposed to some event so terrible that it threatened to drive them insane. Even though he survived, his mind is not what it once was. The DM must select either Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma, and reduce its score to 5 to reflect this weakness. (This could seriously impair spellcasting abilities.)<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character made an enemy of a dragon. Whether he ran afoul of the beast by stealing from it, thwarting one of its plans, or simply experiencing bad luck, the dragon has decided that this character must die. The DM should determine which dragon the character has offended.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character has managed to become the enemy of an entire demihuman or humanoid race. Whatever his crime, members of that race generally loathe the character and seek to destroy them when they encounter them. The DM should determine the race that hates the character.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character once owned some great item, perhaps an incredibly valuable gem or a magical item of glory. This object has been taken from them, leaving the character with an insatiable desire to reclaim his treasure. This relic, however, has found its way into the hands of a creature far more powerful than the character, perhaps even a dragon. The character will not rest until he reclaims the item or dies in the attempt. The DM should determine what the item was and who currently has it.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>Through some mishap, the character has some alter personality. Perhaps this personality is a spirit who possesses them, or it might be a second personality which surfaces in times of stress. When the character's darker half comes to the surface, he behaves in ways unthinkable to his 'normal' self.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character has a seemingly imaginary enemy. This might be the spirit of a long-dead foe, an extra-planar being or untold evil, or a delusion born of the character's disturbed mind. The nature of this enemy should be decided by the DM. When the imaginary villain attacks, it will be difficult for the character to convince his companions that he is in real danger. Before long, they may begin to doubt his sanity or sincerity, as they never find any evidence to support the character's assertions that he has been menaced.<BR/></lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry><BR/>The character has frequent periods of missing time. The length of these blackouts varies, but they generally run about an hour. The character has no memory at all of what happens during this time, but he associates great feelings of anxiety with them. Exactly what happens to the character during these periods is up to the DM.<BR/></lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="weakness">
		<lookup-entry>Aggressive</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Angry</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Apathetic</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Aimless</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Aloof</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Amoral</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Annoying</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Argumentative</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Arrogant</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Bewildered</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Blunt</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Blustering</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Clingy</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Clumsy</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Conceited</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Crude</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Cynical</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Domineering</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Fearful</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Hesitant</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Rude</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Impulsive</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Irritable</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Ponderous</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="needs">
		<lookup-entry>Community - Belonging</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Communication</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Cooperation</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Equality</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Inclusion</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Mutuality</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Participation</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Partnership</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Self-expression</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Community - Sharing</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Appreciation</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Attention</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Closeness</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Companionship</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Harmony</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Intimacy</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Love</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Nurturing</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Sexual Expression</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Support</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Tenderness</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Connection - Warmth</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Freedom - Autonomy</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Freedom - Choice</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Freedom - Ease</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Freedom - Independence</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Acceptance</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Care</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Compassion</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Consideration</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Empathy</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Kindness</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Mutual Recognition</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Respect</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - To be witnessed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - To be understood</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - To be trusted</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Purpose - Understanding of others</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Authenticity</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Competence</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Creativity</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Dignity</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Growth</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Healing</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Honesty</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Integrity</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Self Acceptance</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Self Care</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Self Connection</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Self Knowledge</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Self Realization</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Meaning - Self Importance</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Leisure - Humor</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Leisure - Joy</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Leisure - Play</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Leisure - Pleasure</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Leisure - Rejuvenation</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Subsistence - Food</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Subsistence - Health</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Subsistence - Safety</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Subsistence - Sleep</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Subsistence - Rest</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Subsistence - Shelter</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Subsistence - Touch</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Consistency</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Order</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Structure</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Peace</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Peace of mind</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Protection</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Safety</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Stability</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Security - Trusting</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Understanding - Awareness</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Understanding - Clarity</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Understanding - Discovery</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Understanding - Learning</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Understanding - Existential</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Understanding - Stimulation</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="desires">
		<lookup-entry>Acceptance</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Curiosity</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Eating</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Family</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Honor</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Idealism</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Independence</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Order</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Physical Exercise</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Power</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Romance</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Saving</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Social Contact</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Status</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Tranquility</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Vengeance</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="enemies">
		<lookup-entry>Rivals - Cultural</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Rivals - Econimic</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Rivals - Personal</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Rivals - Personal</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Forces - Nature</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Forces - Supernatural</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Forces - Time</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Ally - Betrayal</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Ally - Poor Choices</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Interfering Authority</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Internal Saboteur</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry></lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

</generator>
