

<generator start-xpath="//lookup-table[@key = 'D']/lookup-entry" escape="%">
<LegalInformation>
  <Notice>
    LEGAL INFORMATION
    Permission to copy, modify and distribute this document is granted
    solely through the use of the Open Gaming License, Version 1.0a.
    All material herein is being released using the Open Gaming
    License Version 1.0a.  You should read and understand the terms of
    that license before using this material.  

    Within this XML document, all information is Open Game Content 
    unless noted otherwise.  Open Game Content is indicated by the 
    LegalStatus attribute of any tag.  This can have values of 
    &quot;open&quot;, &quot;closed&quot;, or &quot;pi&quot; 
    (for Product Identity), where &quot;open&quot; is the 
    default.  All child tags are assumed to share the same 
    value as their most recent parent tag.  
  </Notice>

  <OpenGameLicense type="Wizards" version="1.0a">
    OPEN GAME LICENSE Version 1.0a 
    The following text is the property of Wizards of the Coast,
    Inc. and is Copyright 2000 Wizards of the Coast, Inc
    (&quot;Wizards&quot;).  All Rights Reserved. 
    1. Definitions: 
    (a) &quot;Contributors&quot; means the copyright and/or trademark
    owners who have contributed Open Game Content; 
    (b) &quot;Derivative Material&quot; means copyrighted material
    including derivative works and translations (including into other
    computer languages), potation, modification, correction, addition, 
    extension, upgrade, improvement, compilation, abridgment or other 
    form in which an existing work may be recast, transformed or
    adapted; 
    (c) &quot;Distribute&quot; means to reproduce, license, rent,
    lease, sell, broadcast, publicly display, transmit or otherwise
    distribute; 
    (d) &quot;Open Game Content&quot; means the game mechanic and
    includes the methods, procedures, processes and routines to the
    extent such content does not embody the Product Identity and is an
    enhancement over the prior art and any additional content clearly
    identified as Open Game Content by the Contributor, and means any
    work covered by this License, including translations and
    derivative works under copyright law, but specifically excludes
    Product Identity. 
    (e) &quot;Product Identity&quot; means product and product line
    names, logos and identifying marks including trade dress;
    artifacts; creatures characters; stories, storylines, plots,
    thematic elements, dialogue, incidents, language, artwork,
    symbols, designs, depictions, likenesses, formats, poses,
    concepts, themes and graphic, photographic and other visual or
    audio representations; names and descriptions of characters,
    spells, enchantments, personalities, teams, personas, likenesses
    and special abilities; places, locations, environments, creatures,
    equipment, magical or supernatural abilities or effects, logos,
    symbols, or graphic designs; and any other trademark or registered
    trademark clearly identified as Product identity by the owner of
    the Product Identity, and which specifically excludes the Open
    Game Content; 
    (f) &quot;Trademark&quot; means the logos, names, mark, sign,
    motto, designs that are used by a Contributor to identify itself
    or its products or the associated products contributed to the Open
    Game License by the Contributor; 
   (g) &quot;Use&quot;, &quot;Used&quot; or &quot;Using&quot; means to
    use, distribute, copy, edit, format, modify, translate and
    otherwise create Derivative Material of Open Game Content. 
   (h) &quot;You&quot; or &quot;Your&quot; means the licensee in terms
    of this agreement. 
    2. The License: This License applies to any Open Game Content that 
    contains a notice indicating that the Open Game Content may only
    be Used under and in terms of this License.  You must affix such a 
    notice to any Open Game Content that you Use.  No terms may be
    added to or subtracted from this License except as described by
    the License itself.  No other terms or conditions may be applied
    to any Open Game Content distributed using this License.  
    3. Offer and Acceptance: By Using the Open Game Content You
    indicate Your acceptance of the terms of this License. 
    4. Grant and Consideration: In consideration for agreeing to use
    this License, the Contributors grant You a perpetual, worldwide, 
    royalty-free, non-exclusive license with the exact terms of this
    License to Use, the Open Game Content. 
    5. Representation of Authority to Contribute: If You are
    contributing original material as Open Game Content, You represent
    that Your Contributions are Your original creation and/or You have
    sufficient rights to grant the rights conveyed by this License.  
    6. Notice of License Copyright: You must update the COPYRIGHT
    NOTICE portion of this License to include the exact text of the
    COPYRIGHT NOTICE of any Open Game Content You are copying,
    modifying or distributing, and You must add the title, the
    copyright date, and the copyright holder's name to the COPYRIGHT
    NOTICE of any original Open Game Content you Distribute. 
    7. Use of Product Identity: You agree not to Use any Product
    Identity, including as an indication as to compatibility, except
    as expressly licensed in another, independent Agreement with the
    owner of each element of that Product Identity.  You agree not to
    indicate compatibility or co-adaptability with any Trademark or
    Registered Trademark in conjunction with a work containing Open
    Game Content except as expressly licensed in another, independent
    Agreement with the owner of such Trademark or Registered
    Trademark.  The use of any Product Identity in Open Game Content
    does not constitute a challenge to the ownership of that Product
    Identity.  The owner of any Product Identity used in Open Game
    Content shall retain all rights, title and interest in and to that
    Product Identity.   
    8. Identification: If you distribute Open Game Content You must
    clearly indicate which portions of the work that you are 
    distributing are Open Game Content.  
    9. Updating the License: Wizards or its designated Agents may
    publish updated versions of this License.  You may use any
    authorized version of this License to copy, modify and distribute
    any Open Game Content originally distributed under any version of
    this License.  
    10. Copy of this License: You MUST include a copy of this License
    with every copy of the Open Game Content You Distribute. 
    11. Use of Contributor Credits: You may not market or advertise
    the Open Game Content using the name of any Contributor unless You
    have written permission from the Contributor to do so. 
    12. Inability to Comply: If it is impossible for You to comply
    with any of the terms of this License with respect to some or all
    of the Open Game Content due to statute, judicial order, or
    governmental regulation then You may not Use any Open Game
    Material so affected. 
    13. Termination: This License will terminate automatically if You
    fail to comply with all terms herein and fail to cure such breach
    within 30 days of becoming aware of the breach.  All sublicenses
    shall survive the termination of this License.  
    14. Reformation: If any provision of this License is held to be
    unenforceable, such provision shall be reformed only to the extent 
    necessary to make it enforceable. 
    15. COPYRIGHT NOTICE 
    Open Game License v 1.0a Copyright 2000, Wizards of the Coast, Inc. 
    System Rules Document Copyright 2000, Wizards of the Coast, Inc.; 
    Authors Jonathan Tweet, Monte Cook, Skip Williams, based on
    original material by E. Gary Gygax and Dave Arneson. 
    Conversion of System Rules Document monster information to XML
    format Copyright 2001 John Hanju Kim.  
  </OpenGameLicense>
</LegalInformation>

  <!-- Default trap types. -->
	<lookup-table key="D">
		<lookup-entry>%S3%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>%S2%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>%S1%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>%C%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>%M%</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trigger mechanism -->
	<lookup-table key="T">
		<lookup-entry>Door or trapdoor trigger</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Switch or latch trigger</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Trip wire or floor pressure plate trigger</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Magical trigger</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>



  <!-- Creature Traps...Clerics! -->
  <lookup-table key="C">
    <lookup-entry>%CC% %CS% stand above the portal on a ledge %DS% up. They stand by a crate rocks near the ledge. Upon spoting an intruder, they push the crate so it crashes down upon them. Dexterity saving throw (DC 12) or take 2d6 bludgeoning damage. They then jump down from the ledge to attack, apply falling damage to each creature.</lookup-entry>
    <lookup-entry>%CC% %CS% stand above the portal on a ledge %DS% up. They hold a crate full of rocks between them. Upon spoting an intruder, they drop the crate so it crashes down upon them. Dexterity saving throw (DC 12) or take 2d6 bludgeoning damage. They then jump down from the ledge to attack, apply falling damage to each of the creatures.</lookup-entry>
    <lookup-entry>%CC% %CS% stand in an alcove to the sides of the door. One is tied by a rope to a suspended crate of rocks. Upon spoting an intruder, it moves triggering the crate to drop so it crashes down upon the intruder. Dexterity saving throw (DC 12) or take 2d6 bludgeoning damage. They then step out to attack.</lookup-entry>
  </lookup-table>

  <!-- Magical Traps...Wizards! -->
  <lookup-table key="M">
    <lookup-entry>Flame Jet: CR 2; 1 foot wide, 50 feet long stream of flame (3d6); Reflex %RN% avoids; Search %SD%.</lookup-entry>
    <lookup-entry>Lightning Blast: CR 3; 5 feet wide, 50 feet long blast (3d6); Reflex %RN% avoids; Search %SD%.</lookup-entry>
    <lookup-entry>Globe of Cold: CR 4; 20 foot radius sphere or hemisphere (5d6); Reflex %RN% avoids; Search %SD%.</lookup-entry>
    <lookup-entry>Electrified Floor: CR 4; section of floor (3d10); Reflex %RN% for half damage; Search %SD%.</lookup-entry>
    <lookup-entry>Floor Transforms into acid: CR 6; section of floor (10d6); Reflex %RD% negates; Search %SD%. Note: Successful save means character dives to safety in time.</lookup-entry>
    <lookup-entry>Illusion over Spiked Pit (%DN% deep): CR 3 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %PT%, %AN% melee (1d4 spike attacks for 1d4+2 points of damage per successful hit); Reflex %RN% avoids; Search %SD%.</lookup-entry>
    <lookup-entry>Air Sucked out of room: CR 5; Room takes 4 rounds to decompress and once decompressed air refills in 1d4+1 rounds. Search %SD%. </lookup-entry>
  </lookup-table>

  <!-- Simple Traps...Deadly! -->
	<lookup-table key="S3">
  <lookup-entry>Pit Trap (%DD% Deep): CR 3 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %PT%; Reflex %RD% avoids falling; Search %SD%. Clue %TCft%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Spiked Pit Trap (%DD% Deep): CR 3 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %PT%, %AD% melee (1d4 spikes for $d4$ points of damage per successful hit); Reflex %RD% avoids falling; Search %SD%. Clue %TCft%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Tilting Floor Pit Trap (%DD% Deep): CR 3 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %PT%; Reflex %RD% avoids falling; Search %SD%. Clue %TCft%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Spiked Tilting Floor Pit Trap (%DD% Deep): CR 3 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %AD% mele22e (1d4 spikes for $d4$ points of damage per successful hit); %PT%; Reflex %RS% avoids falling; Search %SD%. Clues %TCft%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Poison Needle Trap: CR 3; %AS% ranged (1d4, plus Poisoned); Reflex %RD% avoids Poisoned; Search %SD%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Poison Dust Trap: CR 3; no attack roll necessary (1d4, plus Poisoned); Reflex %RD% avoids Poisoned; Search %SD%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Poison Gas Trap: CR 3; no attack roll necessary (1d4, plus Poisoned); Gas remains active 1d4 rounds; Reflex %RD% avoids Poisoned; Search %SD%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Hail of Needles: CR 3; %AS% ranged (2d4); Search %SS%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Hail of Bowling Balls Trap: CR 3; %AD% melee 2d6/x6; Reflex %RD% avoids critical damage. Note that room may be designed to curve or ricochet the path of the sphere for 1d4 attacks. Search %SD%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%. </lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Rolling Sphere Trap: CR 3; %AD% melee 6d6; Reflex %RD% avoids critical damage; Search %SD%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%. Note: room may be designed to curve or ricochet the path of the sphere for 1d4 attacks.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Crushing Wall Trap: CR 3; no attack roll required (20d6); Search %SD%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Scything Blade Trap: CR 3; %AN% melee 1d8/x4; Reflex %RD% avoids critical damage; Search %SD%. Clue %TCpt%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Falling Block Trap: CR 3; %AD% melee 6d6; Reflex %RD% avoids critical damage. Can strike all characters in two adjacent specified squares. Search %SD%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Acid Spray Trap: CR 3; no attack roll necessary. Trap releases a spray of acid in %DS% diameter circle; Those caught in the circle take 2d10 acid damage; Reflex %RD% avoids. Search %SD%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Flooding Room Trap: CR 3 (+1 per round of flood); no attack roll necessary (see note below); Note: Room floods in 4 rounds and drains in 1d4+1 rounds. Search %SD%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
</lookup-table>

  <!-- Simple Traps...Dangerous -->
	<lookup-table key="S2">
  <lookup-entry>Caltrops Trap: CR 2; %AN% melee negating armor, shield, and deflection (1 pt dmg/x3, reduced to 1/2 speed); There are scraps of clothing laying about. The shoes or boots have holes in the foot. Reflex %RN% avoids critical damage; Note: 5-ft. reach, target passes over square. Search %SN%. Clues %TCpf% Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Arrow Trap: CR 2; %AN% ranged 1d6/x3; Reflex %RN% avoids critical damage; Note: 200-ft. max range, target determined randomly from those in its path. Search %SN%. Clue %TCpt%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Spear Trap: CR 2; %AN% ranged 1d8/x3; Reflex %RN% avoids critical damage; Note: 200-ft. max range, target determined randomly from those in its path. Search %SN%. Clue %TCpt%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Pit Trap (%DN% Deep): CR 2 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %PT%; Reflex %RN% avoids falling; Search %SN%. Clue %TCft%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Spiked Pit Trap (%DN% Deep): CR 2 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %PT%, %AN% melee (1d4 spikes for $d4$ points of damage per successful hit); Reflex %RN% avoids falling; Search %SN%. Clue %TCft%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Swinging Log Trap: CR 2; %AN% ranged (1d8/x3 crit); Search %SN%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Spiked Swinging Log Trap: CR 2; %AN% ranged (1d8x3, plus 1d4 spikes for 1d4+5 points of damage per spike); Reflex %RN% avoids; Search %SN%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>  
  <lookup-entry>Poison Needle Trap: CR 2; %AN% ranged (1x3, plus greenblood oil poison); Search %SN%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Poison Dust Trap: CR 2; no attack roll necessary (1d4, plus %PG%); Reflex %RS% avoids gas; Search %SS%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Poison Gas Trap: CR 2; no attack roll necessary (1d4, plus %PG%); Reflex %RS% avoids gas; Search %SN%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Hail of Needles: CR 2; %AN% ranged (2d4); Search %SN%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Hail of Bowling Balls Trap: CR 2; %AN% melee 2d6/x3; Reflex %RN% avoids critical damage; Search %SN%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%. Note: room may be designed to curve or ricochet the path of the sphere for 1d4 rounds.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Rolling Sphere Trap: CR 2; %AN% melee 6d6; Reflex %RN% avoids critical damage; Search %SN%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%. Note: room may be designed to curve or ricochet the path of the sphere for 1d4 rounds.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Scything Blade Trap: CR 2; %AN% melee 1d8/x3; Reflex %RN% avoids critical damage; Search %SN%. Clue %TCst%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Falling Block Trap: CR 2; %AN% melee 6d6; Reflex %RN% avoids critical damage; Note: Can strike all characters in two adjacent specified squares. Search %SN%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Large Net Trap: CR 2; %AN% melee. Characters in 10-ft. square are grappled by net (Strength 18) if they fail a Reflex %RN%. Search %SN%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Acid Spray Trap: CR 2; no attack roll necessary. Trap releases a spray of acid in %DS% diameter circle; Those caught in the circle take 2d10 acid damage; Reflex %RN% avoids. Search %SN%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Flooding Room Trap: CR 2 (+1 per round of flood); no attack roll necessary (see note below); Note: Room floods in 4 rounds and drains in 1d4+1 rounds. Search %SN%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Portcullis Trap: CR 2; %AN% melee 3d6/x2; Reflex %RN% avoids critical damage; Note: Damage applies only to those underneath the portcullis. Portcullis blocks passageway. Search %SN%. Clue %TCpt%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
</lookup-table>


  <!-- Simple Traps...Setbacks -->
<lookup-table key="S1">
  <lookup-entry>Caltrops Trap: CR 1; %AS% melee negating armor, shield, and deflection ($S$/x3, reduced to 1/2 speed); Reflex %RS% avoids critical damage; Note: 5-ft. reach, target passes over square. Search %SS%. Clues %TCpf% Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Arrow Trap: CR 1; %AS% ranged $S$/x2; Reflex %RS% avoids critical damage; Note: 200-ft. max range, target determined randomly from those in its path. Search %SS%. Clue %TCpt%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Spear Trap: CR 1; %AS% ranged $S$/x2; Reflex %RS% avoids critical damage; Note: 200-ft. max range, target determined randomly from those in its path. Search %SS%. Clue %TCpt%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Pit Trap (%DS% Deep): CR 1 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %PT%; Reflex %RS% avoids falling; Search %SS%. Clue %TCft%. </lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Spiked Pit Trap (%DS% Deep): CR 2 (+1 per 20 feet of fall); %PT%, %AS% melee (1d4 spikes for $d4$ points of damage per successful hit); Reflex %RS% avoids falling; Search %SS%. Clue %TCft%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Swinging Log Trap: CR 1; %AS% ranged ($S$/x2 crit); Search %SS%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Spiked Swinging Log Trap: CR 2; %AS% ranged ($S$x2, plus 1d4 spikes for $d4$ points of damage per spike); Reflex %RS% avoids; Search %SS%. Clue %TCct%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>  
  <lookup-entry>Poison Needle Trap: CR 1; %AS% ranged (1, plus Poisoned); Reflex %RS% avoids being Poisoned; Search %SS%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Poison Dust Trap: CR 1; no attack roll necessary ($S$, plus %PG%); Reflex %RS% avoids gas; Search %SS%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Poison Gas Trap: CR 1; no attack roll necessary ($S$, plus %PG%); Gas remains active 1d4 rounds; Reflex %RS% avoids gas; Search %SS%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Hail of Needles: CR 1; %AS% ranged ($S$); Search %SS%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Scything Blade Trap: CR 1; %AS% melee $S$/x2; Reflex %RS% avoids critical damage; Search %SS%. Clue %TCst%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
  <lookup-entry>Portcullis Trap: CR 1; %AS% melee $S$/x2; Reflex %RS% avoids critical damage; Note: Damage applies only to those underneath the portcullis. Portcullis blocks passageway. Search %SS%. Clue %TCpt%. Activation %AT%.</lookup-entry>
</lookup-table>


  <!-- Attack bonus - Deadly -->
	<lookup-table key="AD">
		<lookup-entry>+9</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>+10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>+11</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>+12</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Attack bonus - Dangerous -->
	<lookup-table key="AN">
		<lookup-entry>+6</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>+7</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>+8</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Attack bonus - Setback  -->
	<lookup-table key="AS">
		<lookup-entry>+3</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>+4</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>+5</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>


  <!-- Trigger Activation Type -->
	<lookup-table key="AT">
		<lookup-entry>trigger is on a hair trigger. Those probing with a 10 foot pole could avoid the trap. The trigger is a %TD%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>trigger is well maintained. Activate on the first in line. The trigger is a %TD%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>trigger is keyed for the second activation. The trigger is a %TD%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>trigger is unreliable. Use marching order to determine when it activates. The trigger is a %TD%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>trigger is old. Use marching order to determine when it activates. The trigger is a %TD%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>trigger is old and unreliable. Use marching order to determine when it activates. The trigger is a %TD%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>trigger is fragile and breaks after activation. Use marching order to determine when it activates. The trigger is a %TD%</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Creature - Deadly -->
	<lookup-table key="CD">
		<lookup-entry>troll</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Creature - Dangerous -->
	<lookup-table key="CN">
		<lookup-entry>black pudding</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Creature - Setback  -->
	<lookup-table key="CS">
		<lookup-entry>skeletons</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>zombies</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>ghouls</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Creature Count -->
	<lookup-table key="CC">
		<lookup-entry>Two</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Three</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Four</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Creature Attitude -->
	<lookup-table key="CA">
		<lookup-entry>hostile</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>neutral uncertain</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>unfriendly</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>indifferent</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>friendly</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Distance Deadly Fall Lengths -->
	<lookup-table key="DD">
		<lookup-entry>50 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>60 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>80 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>100 feet</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

<!-- Distance Dangerous Fall Lengths -->
	<lookup-table key="DN">
		<lookup-entry>20 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>20 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>20 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>30 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>40 feet</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Distance Setback Fall Lengths -->
	<lookup-table key="DS">
		<lookup-entry>10 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>15 feet</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>20 feet</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>


  <!-- Hit Point Damage is keyed to character level 1-4, 5-10, 11-16, 17-20. Need some more thought to use these . -->
  <!-- Hit Point Damage - Deadly -->
	<lookup-table key="HD">
		<lookup-entry levels="1-4">4d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="5-10">10d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="11-16">18d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="17-20">24d10</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Hit Point Damage - Dangerous -->
	<lookup-table key="HN">
		<lookup-entry levels="1-4">2d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="5-10">4d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="11-16">10d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="17-20">18d10</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Hit Point Damage - Setback  -->
	<lookup-table key="HS">
		<lookup-entry levels="1-4">1d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="5-10">2d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="11-16">4d10</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry levels="17-20">10d10</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Poison Gas -->
	<lookup-table key="PG">
		<lookup-entry>hallucinatory gas scrambles the mind and senses. All Intelligence and Wisdom checks made suffer Disadvantage.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>weakening gas. All Strength and Dexterity checks made suffer Disadvantage.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>dusty gas. Visibility is reduced to 1 foot and creaures gain Blinded condition. </lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>stinging pepper gas. Visibility is reduced to 1 foot and creaures gain Stunned condition. </lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>foul poisoned gas. Creaures gain Poisoned condition. </lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>


  <!-- Pit Trap Contents -->
	<lookup-table key="PT">
		<lookup-entry>The bottom is a hard floor. No attack roll necessary to hit the floor, take 1d6 bludgeoning damage for every ten feet fallen</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The bottom is filled debris and the skeletal remains of an earlier traveler. No attack roll necessary to hit the floor, take 1d6 bludgeoning damage for every ten feet fallen</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The bottom is filled with a shallow pool of acid (DC15 Dexterity check to cling feebly to cracks or take 2d6 acid damage per round). Lucky the acid broke your fall, take half damage for falling (1d6 bludgeoning for every ten feet fallen)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The bottom is filled with a deep pool of %WT% water (DC10 Strength swim check to move 5 feet where failure sinks 5 feet and begins drowning). Your pack or armor might weight you down see the rules for swiming in armor</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The bottom is filled with quicksand (DC10 Strength swim check to move 5 feet where failure sinks 5 feet and begins drowning)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The bottom is filled with tar (DC15 Strength swim check to move 5 feet where failure sinks 5 feet and begins drowning. An open flame will ignite the tar causing fire 1d6 damage every round</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The bottom contains a gelatinous cube (DC15 Dexterity check to avoid landing on it and being immediately engulfed), take 1d6 bludgeoning damage for every ten feet fallen. Try and avoid being engulfed if you can see it</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The bottom contains a black pudding (DC15 Dexterity check to avoid landing directly on it), take 1d6 bludgeoning damage for every ten feet fallen. There are cracks running down the face of the wall that you can navigate with a successful climb check. The black pudding follows</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The bottom contains a %CS%, take 1d6 bludgeoning damage for every ten feet fallen. The creature is %CA%</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>


  <!-- Reflex or Dexterity Save DC - Deadly -->
	<lookup-table key="RD">
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 16)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 17)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 18)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 19)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 20)</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Reflex or Dexterity Save DC - Dangerous -->
	<lookup-table key="RN">
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 12)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 13)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 14)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 15)</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Reflex or Dexterity Save DC - Setback  -->
	<lookup-table key="RS">
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 10)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>save (DC 11)</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trap Seach and Disable DCs - Deadly -->
	<lookup-table key="SD">
		<lookup-entry>(DC 25); Disable Device (DC 26)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 26); Disable Device (DC 25)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 27); Disable Device (DC 25)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 28); Disable Device (DC 30)</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

    <!-- Trap Seach and Disable DCs - Dangerous -->
	<lookup-table key="SN">
		<lookup-entry>(DC 25); Disable Device (DC 26)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 26); Disable Device (DC 25)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 27); Disable Device (DC 25)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 28); Disable Device (DC 30)</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trap Seach and Disable DCs - Setback -->
	<lookup-table key="SS">
		<lookup-entry>(DC 20); Disable Device (DC 20)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 20); Disable Device (DC 20)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 20); Disable Device (DC 20)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 20); Disable Device (DC 20)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 20); Disable Device (DC 25)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 21); Disable Device (DC 20)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 21); Disable Device (DC 25)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 22); Disable Device (DC 20)</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>(DC 22); Disable Device (DC 22)</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trap Clue - Piercing trap-->
	<lookup-table key="TCpt">
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is an old, skeleton. Missing some bones but looks to have been stabbed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is an old, skull. Looks to have been stabbed in the face</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There some scraps and debris. It is clothing, an old shirt. Looks pierced through and shows old, dried blood</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There some scraps. It is clothing, an old pant leg. Looks pierced through and shows old, dried blood</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There some scraps. It is clothing, an old pack. It does not look servicable. It apears to have been pierced through the back</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There some scraps. It is clothing, an old hat. Looks pierced through and shows old, dried blood</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There some scraps. It is clothing, an old cap. Looks pierced through and shows old, dried blood</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There some scraps. It is an old helm. It does not look servicable. Looks pierced through and shows old, dried blood</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There some scraps. It is part of an old %TCpta%. It does not look servicable. Yep, it pierced through the %TCptb% and shows old, dried blood</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="TCpta">
		<lookup-entry>shirt</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>chainmail shirt</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>leather shirt</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>padded armor shirt</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>studded leather shirt</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>scale mail shirt</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>robe</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

	<lookup-table key="TCptb">
		<lookup-entry>heart</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>lung</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>liver</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>kidneys</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>stomach</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>gallbladder</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>


  <!-- Trap Clue - Piercing Foot-->
	<lookup-table key="TCpf">
		<lookup-entry>There is a shoe lying about that has a bloody hole in the sole</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The are a pair of discarded boots. The toe has a hole in one and a hole in the heel of the other</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is old blood on the floor leading to the their entrance. It appears that someone step in blood and left a track</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>The floor shows some old blood splatters. It is a pooling of blood</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is a toe on the floor. It is the big toe and looks decayed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is a toe on the floor. They appear to be the little toes and look decayed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is a bone on the floor. It appears to be someone's big toe</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trap Clue - Falling pit trap-->
	<lookup-table key="TCft">
		<lookup-entry>There is an old hat lying about. No sign of the owner</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is an old cap lying about. No sign of the owner</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is an battered helm lying about. No sign of the owner</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is an pack lying about. It contains some decayed rations</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is a busted grappling hook. It does not look servicable as the tines are bent</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is a short, loose line of rope. It is old and does not look servicable. The end is frayed and the rest of it can not be found</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is an sword lying about. It is old, rusted. The tip has snapped off</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There are some marks on the floor. They are scraches. You notice an old finger nail and dried blood</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>A spike has been nailed into the floor</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trap Clue - Slashing trap-->
	<lookup-table key="TCst">
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is a skeletal hand. It looks severed. Must have been called lefty</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is a skeletal foot but no sign of the owner. It looks severed. He must be called shorty</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is a skeletal arm. It looks severed. Someone is probably missing it</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is a skeletal leg. It looks severed. What did he do? walk away</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>It looks like there is a body part. It is an old, decayed hand. A ring was removed from the finger. It looks severed.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Someone left something behind. There is an old, decayed foot lying on the floor. Anyone need one boot. It looks severed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>It appears there is a body part here. There is an old, decayed arm. It looks severed. It almost looks as if it was pointing</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>It looks like there is a body part here. There is an old,decayed leg. It looks severed</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trap Clue - Crushing trap-->
	<lookup-table key="TCct">
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is a skeletal hand. It looks crushed. Must have been called lefty</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is a skeletal foot but no sign of the owner. It looks crushed. He must be called shorty</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is a skeletal arm. It looks crushed. Someone is probably missing it</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>There is are bones. It is a skeletal leg. It looks crushed. What did he do? walk away</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>It looks like there is a body part. It is an old, decayed hand. A ring was removed from the finger. It looks crushed.</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>Someone left something behind. There is an old, decayed foot lying on the floor. Anyone need one boot. It looks crushed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>It appears there is a body part here. There is an old, decayed arm. It looks crushed. It almost looks as if it was pointing</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>It looks like there is a body part here. There is an old,decayed leg. It looks crushed</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>


  <!-- Trigger Clue - Players need clues -->
	<lookup-table key="TCa">
		<lookup-entry>crushed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>severed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>burnt</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trigger Clue  -->
	<lookup-table key="TCb">
		<lookup-entry>decaying</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>skeletal</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trigger Clue  -->
	<lookup-table key="TCc">
		<lookup-entry>hand</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>foot</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>head</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>arm</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>leg</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>


  <!-- Trigger Disable  -->
	<lookup-table key="TD">
		<lookup-entry>door %TT%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>floor %TF%</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>step %TF%</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trigger floor plate  -->
	<lookup-table key="TF">
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by first pushing a hidden reset button</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by first pulling a hidden reset lever</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by first pulling a hidden reset cord</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by first sliding a disguised reset handle</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by first stepping on a hidden reset tile</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by heat from %TH% turning a hidden reset fan tumbler</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by water poured into a hidden drain to reset a balance vase </lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by water poured into a hidden drain to reset a mill tumbler </lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by key used to reset a lock </lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by %TS% to reset a balance line</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by %TS% to reset a tension line</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by %TS% blown to reset a switch</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate that activates when %TO% and disabled by key press to reset a switch</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>plate has been ripped out and thrown to the side. The trap is broken but the characters do not know this for sure.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trigger reset heat  -->
	<lookup-table key="TH">
		<lookup-entry>candle</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>lamp</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>torch</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>burning incense</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trigger on or off  -->
	<lookup-table key="TO">
		<lookup-entry>stepped on</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>stepped off</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>crossed</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>light over it is blocked</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>light over it is crossed</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trigger reset sound tone  -->
	<lookup-table key="TS">
		<lookup-entry>bell is struck</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>chord is plucked</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>chimes are blown</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Trigger handle turned  -->
	<lookup-table key="TT">
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by turning left and activates by turning right to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by pulling a hidden reset cord and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a hard push in and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a hard pull out and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a hard pull on knocker and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a hard push on the knocker and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by sliding knocker left and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by sliding knocker right and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by pushing knocker up and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by pushing knocker down and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a hard pull on the lock and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a hard push on the lock and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by using key in lock and activates by turning to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a strong lift up and activates when door handle is pushed to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a strong lift up and activates when door handle is pulled to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a strong push down and activates when door handle is pushed to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob which disables by a strong push down and activates when door handle is pulled to open</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>knob is dangling from the door. The trap is broken but the player do not know this for sure.</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

  <!-- Water Type or quality -->
	<lookup-table key="WT">
		<lookup-entry>putrid</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>stagnant</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>brackish</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>fresh</lookup-entry>
		<lookup-entry>salt</lookup-entry>
	</lookup-table>

</generator>


