<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml:stylesheet href="feats.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feats>
<category name="General">
<feat>
<name>Knock-Down</name>
<description>Your mighty blows can knock foes off their feet.</description>
<prerequisites>Str 15+, BAB +2, Improved Trip</prerequisites>
<benefits>
<p>Whenever you deal 10 or more points of damage 
to your opponent in melee with a single attack, you may make 
a trip attack as a free action against the same target. Use 
of this feat cannot be combined with Improved Trip to 
generate an extra attack, and successful use of this feat 
does not grant an extra attack through the Cleave or Great 
Cleave feats. If you fail your opponents can attempt a 
Strength check to try and trip you.</p>
</benefits>
</feat>
<feat>
<name>Improved Great Cleave</name>
<description>A character may take a 5' step while cleaving.</description>
<prerequisites>BAB +9, Great Cleave</prerequisites>
<benefits>
<p>As Great Cleave, except that you may take a 
5' step before making the Cleave attack. You can only take one 
5' step in between Cleave attacks. If you have already 
taken a 5' step you may not take another in the same round.
</p>
</benefits>
</feat>
<feat>
<name>Flexible Reach</name>
<description>
You may choke up or down on a hafted polearm 
to threaten and attack adjacent foes.</description>
<prerequisites>Dex 13+, BAB +4, Combat Reflexes</prerequisites>
<benefits>
<p>You can choke up or down on a hafted polearm as 
a free action. This allows you to attack adjacent 
foes and still threaten areas the polearm could normally 
reach. You cannot perform this action while flanked.</p>
</benefits>
</feat>
<feat>
<name>Polearm Grapple</name>
<description>
You are trained in not only striking opponents but 
also in pinning the foe where they stand.
</description>
<prerequisites>Int 13+, Expertise</prerequisites>
<benefits>
<p>
Whenever you hit with a polearm and deal damage you may 
initiate a grapple as a free action without provoking 
an attack of opportunity from that opponent. If you succeed 
you have pinned you opponent with your polearm. If you fail 
your grapple check you may drop your polearm to avoid 
being grappled.
</p>
</benefits>
</feat>
<feat>
<name>Weapon Mastery</name>
<description>
Over years of study you have mastered the use of a particular weapon.
</description>
<prerequisites>BAB +9, Weapon Specialization</prerequisites>
<benefits>
<p>
Your familiarity with your weapon of choice is so great that 
you can strike with incredible accuracy and ferocity. You 
receive an additional +2 hit and +1 damage with it. This effect
stacks with Weapon Specialization.
</p>
</benefits>
</feat>
<feat>
<name>Quick Sheath</name>
<description>
You are skilled at quickly handling your weapons.
</description>
<prerequisites>BAB +1</prerequisites>
<benefits>
<p>
You can sheath a weapon as a free action instead of as a 
move-equivalent action. You may apply this ability on any 
weapon that you have taken the Weapon Focus or Weapon Finesse 
feats.  You need only take this feat once. This feat stacks 
with Quickdraw allowing you to switch weapons instantaneously.
</p>
</benefits>
</feat>
<feat>
<name>Defensive Study</name>
<description>
You are skilled at observing your opponents fighting and 
creating openings in combat.
</description>
<prerequisites>Int 13+, BAB +4, Dodge</prerequisites>
<benefits>
<p>
When executing the Total Defense action you may subtract a
number from your AC for the round and apply the same number 
to your attack rolls in the following round.  This number
may not exceed your total dodge bonus for the round.  This 
attack bonus is not applied to your damage rolls.
</p>
</benefits>
</feat>
<feat>
<name>Improved Defensive Study</name>
<description>
You are an expert in observing combatants.
</description>
<prerequisites>Int 13+, BAB +9, Defensive Study</prerequisites>
<benefits>
<p>
As the Defensive Study feat, except you no longer need to
execute the Total Defense action when applying the Defensive
Study feat.  The attack bonus still occurs in the following
round.
</p>
</benefits>
</feat>
</category>
</feats>
